Guide to the Langdon Gilkey Papers 1921-2004
University of Chicago Library
Gilkey, Langdon. Papers
1921-2004
11 linear feet (23 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Langdon Brown Gilkey taught at the Divinity School of the University of Chicago from 1963 until his retirement in 1989. He was a prominent protestant theologian, an expert on the relation between science and religion, and a key respondent to the rise of intelligent design as a way of teaching creationism. During 1940-1945 he taught at Yenching University (now part of Peking University) in Beijing, China, then occupied by the Japanese, and from 1943 to 1945 he was interned along with other Allied civilians at the Weihsien Internment Camp (or Weihsien Civilian Assembly Center). The collection contains official and personal correspondence, notes, manuscripts and typescripts, newspaper clippings, postcards, periodicals and other publications, photographs, and administrative documents dating between 1934 and 2004. The bulk of the material dates between 1940-1945 and 1954-2004. The papers primarily document Langdon Gilkey’s life in China during the Second World War and his professional career as theologian, academician, and professor at the Divinity School of the University of Chicago and other institutions.
Information on Use
Access
Series VI of the collection contains evaluative student materials, which are restricted for eighty years after the date of record creation.
Biographical Note
Langdon Brown Gilkey (b. 1919 and d. 2004) was born and raised in Chicago, Illinois. His father, Rev. Charles W. Gilkey (1882-1968), was chaplain of the Rockefeller Memorial Chapel on the campus of the University of Chicago and Associate Dean of the Divinity School. Langdon Gilkey acquired his A.B. from Harvard University in 1940 and a joint Ph.D. from Columbia University and Union Theological Seminary in 1954. Gilkey taught at Union Theological Seminary in New York from 1949 to 1950, Vassar College from 1951 to 1954, and Vanderbilt University from 1954 to 1963. In July 1963 he was appointed to the faculty of the Divinity School of the University of Chicago. After his retirement in 1989, Gilkey taught periodically at the University of Virginia and Georgetown University.
From 1940 to 1942, Gilkey taught at Yenching University (now part of Peking University) in Beijing, China, which was then occupied by the Japanese. After the attack on Pearl Harbor, the United States and Japan formally entered in to war, and Gilkey was interned along with other Allied civilians by the Japanese in the Weihsien Internment Camp in Shandong, China from 1943 until the end of the war; this act may be seen as a retaliation to the forceful relocation of Japanese Americans by the United States. Gilkey discussed the formative impact of this experience in Shantung Compound: The Story of Men and Women Under Pressure (1968), and he revisited the compound in 1995.
A prominent American Protestant Theologian, Langdon Gilkey authored fifteen books and several hundred scholarly articles during his career. He systematically outlined his theology in three major works: Naming the Whirlwind: The Renewal of God-Language (1969), Repeating the Whirlwind: A Christian Interpretation of History (1976), and Message and Existence: An Introduction to Christian Theology (1979). He is best known for his writings on science and religion, including Creationism on Trial: God at Little Rock (1985) that builds upon his testimony at McLean v. Arkansas, a landmark case on the teaching of creationism in public schools. Gilkey wrote authoritatively on twentieth-century theologians Reinhold Niebuhr and Paul Tillich; both were his teachers at Union Theological Seminary. Gilkey also fostered exchanges between theological traditions. He offered a Protestant perspective on the theological movements of Vatican II in Catholicism Confronts Modernity (1975). He authored articles and reviews on Christian-Buddhist dialogues and taught at Kyoto University in Japan in 1975.
Scope Note
The Langdon Gilkey Papers are organized into six series: Series I: Personal; Series II: Correspondence; Series III: Teaching; Series IV: Writings and Research; Series V: Audio-Visual; and Series VI: Restricted. The collection contains official and personal correspondence, notes, manuscripts and typescripts, newspaper clippings, postcards, periodicals and other publications, photographs, and administrative documents dating between 1934 and 2004. The bulk of the material dates between 1940-1945 and 1954-2004. The papers primarily document Langdon Gilkey’s life in China during the Second World War and his professional career as theologian, academician, and professor at the Divinity School of the University of Chicago and other institutions.
Series I, Personal, contains materials primarily related to Gilkey’s pre-professional life and personal activities. Highlights of the series are materials documenting Langdon Gilkey’s activities in Japanese-occupied China during the Second World War from 1940-1945. These materials include letters between Gilkey and his family. Many of them show the difficult modes of communication between Allied-controlled and occupied territories during the Second World War; after Pearl Harbor, Gilkey had to rely on middlepersons or the Red Cross to contact his family. Also notable are records of the kitchen of the Weihsien Internment Camp (1943-1945); the Japanese let the civilian internees govern the Camp by themselves, and from 1943 to 1945 Gilkey worked as a manager of the Camp’s kitchen. Also included are pamphlets, maps, and other materials related to Yenching University (now part of Peking University). This series also includes some of Charles Gilkey’s papers.
Series II, Correspondence, contains Gilkey’s letters from and to his professional colleagues, including his past students, and other academic institutions. Due to their evaluative nature, letters of recommendation are included in Series VI, restricted. Gilkey’s personal correspondence from China is included in Series I, Personal.
Series III, Teaching, contains Gilkey’s lecture notes, syllabi, and other materials related to his teaching at Union Theological Seminary, Vassar College, Vanderbilt University, the Divinity School of the University of Chicago, the University of Virginia, and Georgetown University. It also contains materials documenting Gilkey’s teaching at Japan (1975) and Hong Kong (2001-2002).
Series IV, Writings and Research, constitutes the bulk of the collection. It mainly consists of Gilkey’s writings in a variety of formats: notes, conference presentations, articles, talks, speeches, sermons, and court testimonials. It also includes his collection of academic essays, articles, and periodicals, as well as the travel documents, pamphlets, and correspondence specifically related to the academic events he attended. Highlights of this series are drafts of Gilkey’s publications and different versions of his articles or conference presentations.
Series V, Audio-Visual, consists of portraits of Gilkey and a few unidentified photographs, which could be family pictures.
Series VI: Restricted, contains Gilkey’s evaluated work from college and graduate school, and student grades, letters of recommendation, and other evaluative materials from his teaching. Materials are restricted for eighty years after the date of record creation.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Gilkey, Charles Whitney Papers
Subject Headings
Gilkey, Langdon Brown, 1919-2004; Gilkey, Charles Whitney, 1882-1968; University of Chicago; Theology—Study and teaching—United States; Theology—United States; Creationism—United States; Weihsien Civilian Assembly Center
INVENTORY
- Series I: Personal
  This series mainly documents Gilkey’s pre-Professional life and personal activities. It also includes Charles Gilkey’s correspondence in relation to Langdon Gilkey’s activities in China, as well as Charles Gilkey’s papers. Materials are ordered chronologically.
  - College and Graduate School Papers, circa 1933-1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence from China [1/3], 1940 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence from China [2/3], 1941 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence from China [3/3], 1942-1495 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Writings in China, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Weihsien Internment Camp Records [1/2], 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Weihsien Internment camp Records [2/2], 1945 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - “Life in an Internment Camp,” 1945 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence of Charles Gilkey, 1928-1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Charles Gilkey’s Papers, 1921-70 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Harvard 25th Reunion, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Koinonia Partners, Brochures and Newsletters, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - The University of Chicago Magazine, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Memorial Service for Ioan Culianu, University of Chicago, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous materials on health and medicine, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - “Fifty Years Later: Shantung Compound Revisited,” 1995 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper Clipping – The Highlander, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper Clipping – Washington Post, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - News Paper Clipping – The New York Times, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series II: Correspondence
  This series mainly contains Gilkey’s correspondence with professional colleagues and academic institutions. Materials are ordered according to the last names of the correspondents.
  - Anderson, Per, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Bessler, 1990-1997 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Billington, John, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Brown, Charles, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Center for Theology and the Natural Sciences, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Christopherson, John, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Creel, Austin B., 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Deschich, Carol, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Hartshorne, Charles, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Hefner, Philip, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Hendricks, Charles, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Hersey, John, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Hoshinski, Thomas, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Lippitz, Charles, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Mamouth College, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - NEH Institute, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - O’Brien, Bill, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Ogletree, T.W., 1969 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Olivetti, Marco M., 1991 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Pasewark, Kyle, 1993-1995 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Payne, Richard J, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Pool, Jeff D., 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Pultz, David, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Reeves, Gene, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Rike, Jennifer, 1995-1996 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Scharf, Uwe Carsten, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Starr, Cole, 1996-1997 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Sifton, Elisabeth, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Spahn, Jeffrey, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Stetson University, 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Vahanian, Gabriel, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Wilson, Richard F, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1990-1998 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Summer Correspondence, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1993-1996 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Series III: Teaching
  This series contains Gilkey’s lecture notes, syllabi, and other materials related to his teaching. Materials are grouped according to the related courses and institutions and are ordered chronologically.
  - Vanderbilt University – Seminar on Augustine, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Vanderbilt University and University of Chicago – “History of Christine Doctrine,” 1955, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Vanderbilt University – Lectures for Ministers Conference, 1955-57 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Vanderbilt University – Seminars on Reinhold Niebuhr and Paul Tillich, 1956-1961 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Vanderbilt University – “The Church and the World,” 1958, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Vanderbilt University and the University of Chicago – “History of Christian Doctrine,” 1959, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Vanderbilt University – Courses on Luther and Calvin, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Vanderbilt University – REL 356 “Development of Liberal Theology,” 1963 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - University of Chicago – “The Nature of the Church,” 1962-75 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - University of Chicago – “History of Christian Thought,” 1965 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - University of Chicago and University of Virginia – Miscellaneous, 1966-93 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - University of Chicago – CT 315/CT 461 “Problematic Theology/Issues and Problems in Contemporary Theology,” 1969-1972 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - University of Chicago – “Philosophy of Religion II,” circa 1970 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - University of Chicago – Courses on Alfred North Whitehead, 1972-1976 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - University of Chicago – “Religious Thoughts to 1500,” 1975 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - University of Chicago – CT 305 “Introduction to Theology,” 1976-1980 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - University of Chicago – “Theology of History II,” 1976 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - University of Chicago – Courses on Niebuhr, 1977-1984 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - University of Chicago – “History, Historicity, and Narrative,” 1978-1983 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - University of Chicago – SC 321 “Religion and Modern Culture,” 1983, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - University of Chicago – Various Lecture Notes, 1984-1987 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - University of Chicago – CT 457 “Religion and Science” (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - University of Chicago – CT 405 “Søren Kierkegaard,” 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - University of Chicago – “Doctrine of God” and “God and other Religions,” 1987 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - University of Chicago – CT 499 “Religion and the Religious,” 1988 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - University of Chicago – Teaching Notes, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - University of Virginia – RELG 565 “Theology of Augustine,” 1991-1996 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - University of Virginia – RELG 562 “The Development of Liberal Theology,” 1993 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - University of Virginia – Theology 320 “The Issue of Religious Pluralism,” 1993 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - University of Virginia – RELG 565 “The Philosophy of Whitehead,” 1994 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Lecture at George Washington University, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Courses on Paul Tillich and Reinhold Niebuhr at Various Institutions, 1995-1999 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Georgetown University et al – “Religion and Science,” 1995-1999 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Georgetown University – Theology 320 “Pluralism,” 1995-1997 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - University of Virginia – Theology 138/Religion 347 “Religion and Science,” 1997-1998 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Lecture Notes for Teaching in Japan, 1973-1975 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Teaching Materials for Seminars in Japan, circa 1975 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Chung Chi College, the Chinese University of Hong Kong – RST 2232 “God, Creation, and Eschatology,” 2001-2002 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Lecture on Reinhold Niebuhr, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - “Secularism, Fundamentalism, and the Religious Dimension,” ND circa 2000s (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Series IV: Writings and Research
  This series mainly consists of Gilkey’s academic writings and other documents related to his professional activities. Materials in this series are ordered chronologically.
  - “Leibniz and Santayana: a Rationalist and a Naturalist Compared,” 1940 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Writings of Reinhold Niebuhr, 1942-1945 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Notes on Alfred North Whitehead, 1948-1969 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Notes on Classical Backgrounds, circa 1950 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Luther Reading Notes, circa 1950 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Notes on John Dewey, circa 1950-1954 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - “Maker of Heaven and Earth,” PhD Thesis [1/3], 1950-1954 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - “Maker of Heaven and Earth,” PhD Thesis [2/3], 1950-1954 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - “Maker of Heaven and Earth,” PhD Thesis [3/3], 1950-1954 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Thesis Book I and Notes, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Thesis Book I, 1950-1954 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Thesis Book II, 1950-1954 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Thesis Part III, 1950-1954 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Thesis Part III, 1950-1954 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Articles and Reviews at Vassar College, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Abstract of PhD Thesis, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Papers and Notes at Vassar College, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Articles and Reviews at Vassar College, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Sermons, 1956-1992 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Articles and Reviews at Vanderbilt University, 1956 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Articles and Reviews at Vanderbilt University, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Christianity and Crisis Volume 20, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Two Essays on Biblical Theology, circa 1960 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Articles at Vanderbilt University, 1961-1962 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Articles and Reviews at Vanderbilt University, 1962 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Lectures on Romans in Nashville, 1962 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - “The Idea of Providence in Contemporary Theology,” 1962-1963 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - “Holy, Holy, Holy,” 1963-1964 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Original Manuscripts of New Published Materials, 1963-1969 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - “Some Problems in the Concept of Providence,” circa 1963 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - “How I am making up my mind,’ 1964-1965 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Article in The Baptist Student, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - “Dissolution and Reconstruction in Theology,” 1965 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - “Is God Dead?” 1965 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Notes on Alfred North Whitehead, 1965-1983 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Preface to “Man is Estrangement,” 1965 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Paul Tillich’s Christology, 1965-1980 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - “Projection Theories and Magical Practices,” 1965-1988 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Review, Adams, Paul Tillich’s Philosophy of Culture, Science, and Religions, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Review, Cobb, A Christian Natural Theology, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Review, McKelway, The Systematic Theology of Paul Tillich, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - “Secularism’s Impact on Contemporary Theology, “1965 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - “The Darwinian Controversy and Christian Thought,” circa 1965 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - “The Implications for Theological Reflections of Scientific Breakthroughs,” circa 1965 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Articles, 1966-1975 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Articles and Reviews, 1966-1967 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - “Religion and the Secular University,” 1966-1969 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Review, Löwith, Nature, History, and Existentialism, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - “Social and Intellectual Sources of Contemporary Protestant Theology in America,” 1966-1967 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - “The God is Dead Theology,” (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Time Magazine Articles, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - “The Authority of the Bible,” 1966 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Articles and Reviews, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - “Evolutionary Science and the Dilemma of Freedom and Determinism,” 1967-1968 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - “Security and Modern Theology,” 1967 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - “American Policy and the Just War,” 1968 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - “Modern Myth-Making and the Possibilities on the Twentieth-Century Theology,” 1968 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - “Morality and the Law,” 1968 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Review, Jenkins, The Christian Belief in God, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Review, Schubert, The Reality of God and Other Essays, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - “Student radicals are right,” 1968 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - “The Contribution of Culture to the Reign of God,” 1968-1968 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - “The Idea of God from the Enlightenment to Modern Times,” 1968-1969 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - “The Priesthood in the Modern World View,” 1968 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - “The Problem of God,” 1968-1969 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - “The Religious Dimensions of the Secular,” 1968 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - “Is Faith Possible in a Secular Age,” 1969 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - “Reflection on the End of an Era,” 1969 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - “Anatomy of Reconciliation,” 1969 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Letters and Unpublished Manuscripts, 1969-1970 (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - “The Future of Empirical Theology,” 1969 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - “Trends in Protestant Apologetics,” 1969 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - “Biblical Symbols in a Scientific Culture,” 1970 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Notes, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Notes on Karl Barth, 1970-1991 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - “Religious Dimensions of Scientific Inquiry,” 1970 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Review, Rahner, Spirit in the World, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - “That Mysterious Sleeping Dragon,” 1970 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Theology in the Seventies, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - “Comments on Emmanuel Levinas’s Tonalite et Infini,” 1970-1971 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - “Process Theology,” 1971 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - “The Role of Philosophy,” 1971 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - “The Student Revolt,” 1971 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - “Technology, History, and Liberation,” 1972-1973 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - “The Myth of the Mythless Society,” 1972 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - “To the Bennes: Presumptuous Comments on some of his paintings,” 1972 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Review, Dupre, The Other Dimension, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Review, Niebuhr, Experiential Religion, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - “The Spirit and the Discovery of Truth through Dialogue,” 1972-1973 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Review, Pannenberg, Basic Questions in Theology, 1973-1974 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Speeches, 1973-1974 (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - “The Eternal God: Eternal Ground of New Possibilities,” 1973-1974 (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - “Theology in the Divinity School,” 1973 (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - “The Problem of a Nineteenth Century Theology,” 1973 (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - “The Structure of Academic Revolutions,” 1973 (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - “Reinhold Niebuhr’s Theology of History,” 1973-1974 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Review, Heilbroner, The Human Project, 1974 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - “Robert Heilbroner’s Vision of History,” 1974 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - “The Meaning of Watergate,” 1974 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Lectures in Japan, 1975 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - “The Future of Science,” 1975 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Papers on Secularization,” 1976-1981 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - “The Contribution of Theology to the Comprehension of History,” 1976 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - “The Dialectic of Christian Belief,” 1976 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - “The Search for Meaning,” 1976 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Writings, 1976-1978 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Articles and Notes on Wilfred Cantwell Smith, 1977-1981 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Notes on Cosmologies, circa 1977-1986 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - “Religion and the American Future,” circa 1977 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - The Christian Century, containing exchanges between Langdon Gilkey and Avery Dulles, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - “The Church and the University,” 1977 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - “The Mystery of Being and Non-Being,” 1977 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - “Responses to Peter Berger,” 1978 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - “The Political Dimensions of Theology,” 1978 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - “The Uses of Phenomenology in Systematic Theology,” 1978 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - “Towards a Redefinition of Universal Salvation in Christ,” 1978 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Writings, 1978-1981 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Writings, 1978-1984 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - “History, Providence, and the People of God,” circa 1979 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Papers on Religion and Science, 1979-1980 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - “Scripture and History,” 1979 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - “The AAR and the Anxiety of Non Being,” 1979 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Arts of Ministry, 1989-1982 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - “Church, University, and Culture in Nashville,” circa 1980 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - “Is Religious Faith Possible in an Age of Science,” 1980 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - “Lakatos and the Philosophy of Dubitability,” circa 1980 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - “Philosophy and Theology of History,” 1980 (Box 13, Folder 5)